Register of the Lithuanian subject collection, 1918-1996
Hoover Institution Archives
Lithuanian Subject Collection,
1918-1996
XX812
12 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box (6 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Serial issues, bulletins, newsletters, pamphlets, and other printed matter, relating to various aspects of Lithuanian history, and especially to the movement culminating in re-establishment of Lithuanian independence in 1991, and to subsequent Lithuanian politics and elections.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
Lithuania--History; Nationalism--Lithuania; Lithuania--Politics and government; Elections--Lithuania; Lithuania; Soviet Union
Series Description
- SUBJECT FILE, 1918-1992. (Boxes 1-2)
  Articles, clippings, reports, printed matter, leaflets, and other materials. Arranged alphabetically by subject.
- SERIALS, 1980-1993. (Boxes 2-10)
  Magazines and newspapers published in Lithuania and abroad. Arranged alphabetically by title.
Container List
- SUBJECT FILE, 1918-1992
  - Jews - Lithuania. Prunskis, Juozas, Lithuania's Jews and the Holocaust, n.d. (Box 1., Folder 1)
  - Lietuvos Demokratu Partijos (Folder 2)
  - Lietuvos Persitvarkymo Sajudis (Folder 3-4)
  - Lithuania
    - General (Folder 5)
    - Constitution. Rackauskas, Konstantinas, Lietuvos Konstitucines Teises Klausimais, New York, 1967 (Folder 6)
    - Elections
      - General, 1989-1992 (Folder 7)
      - Polish minority candidates, 1992 (Folder 8)
    - History
      - 1918-1919 (Folder 9)
      - Soviet occupation, 1940-1941 (Folder 10)
      - 1945-1991 (Folder 11)
      - Independence movement, 1989-1990 (Folder 12-13)
    - Soviet heroes. Zimanas, G. O., Vspomnim Poimenno (O Geroe Sovetskogo Soiuza Gubertase Borise), Moscow, 1984 (Folder 14)
- SERIALS, 1980-1993
  - XXI Amzius (Kaunas)
    - 1991: Nos. 1, 11, 17-19, 31 (Box 2., Folder 1)
    - 1992: Nos. 62, 66 (Folder 2)
  - Aistuva (Ukmerge), 1990: Nos. 1, 2 (Folder 3)
  - Aitvaras (Vilnius), 1991: Nos. 3, 4, 6-8 (Folder 4)
  - Akis i Aki (Kaunas), 1990: No. 1 (Folder 5)
  - Aktyvi Sveikata (Kaunas), 1990: Nos. 5, 6 (Folder 6)
  - Aljansas (Vilnius), 1992: Nos. 8, 10, 11, 12 (Folder 7)
  - Alytaus Sajudis (Alytus), 1989: Nos. 13/14, 46, 47 (Folder 8)
  - Amzius (Vilnius), 1992: Nos. 71, 73 (Folder 9)
  - Apie Mus (Vilnius), 1989: No. 11 (Folder 10)
  - Apzvalga (Kaunas)
    - 1990: Nos. 11, 15 (Folder 11)
    - 1992: Nos. 43-52; 1993: No. 9 (Folder 12)
  - Ateities Spindulys (Utena), 1989: No. 1; 1990: Nos. 2, 7 (Folder 13)
  - Atgaiva (Rokiskis), 1989: No. 13; 1990: Nos. 3, 4, 7, 8 (Folder 14)
  - Atgimimas (Vilnius)
    - 1988: Nos. 1-13 (Folder 15)
    - 1992: Nos. 39, 46-51 (Folder 16)
  - Atmintis (Vilnius), 1989: 1 issue (unnumbered) (Folder 17)
  - Atspindziai (Vilnius)
    - 1989: Nos. 1, 2 (Folder 18)
    - 1990: Nos. 1-21; 1991: Nos. 1-5, 7, 9 (Folder 19)
  - Aukso Versis (Vilnius), 1991: No. 1 (Folder 20)
  - Aukstaitis (Kaunas), 1990: Nos. 3, 4 (Folder 21)
  - Ausra (Punsk), 1990: No. 11 (Folder 22)
  - Ausrine (Vilnius), 1988: Nos. 1-3; 1989: Nos. 4, 5; 1990: Nos. 1, 2, 4 (Box 3., Folder 1)
  - Baltu Ainiai (Vilnius), 1991: Nos. 1, 2 (Folder 2)
  - Bendrija (Kaunas), 1989: Nos. 1, 9 (Folder 3)
  - Biciulis (Kaunas), 1989: No. 6 (Folder 4)
  - Biznis (Kaunas), 1991: No. 1 (Folder 5)
  - Blaivioji Lietuva (Vilnius), 1989: Nos. 6, 7, Birzelis, Liepa, Rugpjutis; 1990: Nos. 3, 4 (Folder 6)
  - Caritas (Kaunas), 1991: Nos. 1-8 (Folder 7)
  - Dantis uz Danti (Vilnius), 1991: No. 2 (Folder 8)
  - Darbininku Balsas (Klaipeda), 1989: Nos. 1, 2, 5-9; 1990: No. 11 (Folder 9)
  - Deutsche Nachrichten fur Litauen (Klaipeda), 1989: No. 2; 1990: Nos. 3, 4; 1992: Nos. 5, 7 (Folder 10)
  - Draugyste (Vilnius), 1990: Nos. 51, 65 (Folder 11)
  - Druskininku (Druskininkai), 1990: No. 2 (Folder 12)
  - Druskonis (Druskininkai), 1989: No. 2 (Folder 13)
  - Dubysa (Raseiniai), 1989: No. 9 (Folder 14)
  - Dvidesimt Kapeiku (Kaunas), 1990: Nos. 5, 9, 10, 15-19 (Folder 15)
  - Dzukijos Krasto Laisve (Vilnius), 1991: No. 1 (Folder 16)
  - East Express (Vilnius), 1991: Nos. 17-20, 22, 23; 1992: No. 24 (Folder 17)
  - The Economist of Lithuania (Vilnius), 1990: Nos. 1-3; 1991: No. 1 (Folder 18)
  - Elka (Vilnius), 1990: Nos. 6, 7, 10; 1991: Nos. 1, 3-12 (Folder 19)
  - Erdves (Vilnius), 1990: No. 3 (Box 4., Folder 1)
  - Europos Centras (Vilnius), 1992: Nos. 16, 17 (Folder 2)
  - Europos Lietuvis (London), 1992: Nos. 43-45, 49/50 (Folder 3)
  - Expresas-Rytai Vakarai (Vilnius), 1991: Nos. 19, 20, 23-25, 40, 49, 61 (Folder 4)
  - Fontanas (Kaunas), 1990: No. 1 (Folder 5)
  - Forumas (Vilnius), 1989: Nos. 1, 3; 1990: Nos. 9, 12, 13; 1991: No. 11 (Folder 6)
  - Fotografija (Vilnius), 1990: No. 1 (Folder 7)
  - Fotografu Laikrastis (Vilnius), 1989: No. 14; 1990: Nos. 18, 19 (Folder 8)
  - Gaida (Vilnius), 1989: No. 1 (Folder 9)
  - Gelezmis Vilkas (Vilnius), 1989: No. 8 (Folder 10)
  - Gelupis (Prienai), 1989: Nos. 11-13 (Folder 11)
  - Gimtine (Vilnius), 1992: No. 11 (Folder 12)
  - Gyvasis Zodis (Vilnius), 1992: No. 1 (Folder 13)
  - Hare Krisna (Vilnius), 1989: Nos. 1, 5 (Folder 14)
  - I Saule (Panevezys), 1990: 1 issue (unnumbered) (Folder 15)
  - InformARANTA (Vilnius), 1990: m. sausis (Folder 16)
  - Inzinerine Mintis, 1989: Rugjutis (Folder 17)
  - Jaunoji Karta (Kaunas), 1989: Nos. 4, 9 (Folder 18)
  - Jaunoji Lietuva (Vilnius), 1989: Nos. 2, 3 (Folder 19)
  - Jerusalem of Lithuania (Vilnius), 1992: Nos. 7-9 (Folder 20)
  - Jurbarkietis (Kaunas), 1990: No. 6 (Folder 21)
  - Justitia (Vilnius), 1989: No. 1; 1990: No. 4 (Folder 22)
  - Kalba Motina, 1989: No. 12; 1990: No. 19 (Folder 23)
  - Karys (Vilnius), 1991: No. 1; 1992: Nos. 9-12 (Folder 24)
  - Kauno Aidas (Kaunas)
    - 1988: Nos. 2-7 (Folder 25)
    - 1989: Nos. 1, 13, 16, 21, 26-28 (Folder 26)
    - 1990: No. 12 (Folder 27)
    - 1991: Nos. 1-10, 13-19, 21-28 (Folder 28)
    - 1992: No. 41 (Folder 29)
  - Kauno Laikas (Kaunas), 1991: No. 48 (Folder 30)
  - Kauno Tiesa (Kaunas), 1990: No. 234 (Folder 31)
  - Kelias (Radviliskis), 1990: No. 11 (Folder 32)
  - Keturi Vejai (Kaunas), 1990: No. 1 (Folder 33)
  - Kolona (Vilnius), 1988: No. 2 (Folder 34)
  - Kovoll (Kaunas), 1991: No. 9; 1992: Nos. 36, 37 (Folder 35)
  - Kranklys (Vilnius), 1989: Nos. 1, 5-7, 9, 12, 14-18; 1990: No. 22 (Box 5., Folder 1)
  - Kraziu Aidai (Kraziai), 1989: Nos. 6-13; 1990: Nos. 20, 25 (Folder 2)
  - Krivule (Siauliai), 1989: Nos. 1-3 (Folder 3)
  - Kuntaplis (Vilnius), 1990: No. 52 (Folder 4)
  - Laisva Lietuva, 1991: Nos. 1, 2 (Folder 5)
  - Laisvas Zodis (Panevezys), 1989: Nos. 9, 13-16, 20, 21; 1990: Nos. 35-37, 39-43, 53; 1991: No. 63 (Folder 6)
  - Laisvasis Kaunas (Kaunas), 1991: No. 8 (Folder 7)
  - Laisves Sauklys (Vilnius), 1989: Nos. 12-15 (Folder 8)
  - Lauzas (Vilnius), 1991: No. 1 (Folder 9)
  - Liaudies Kultura (Vilnius), 1992: Nos. 3, 4 (Folder 10)
  - Liepajas Vards (Vilnius)
    - 1990: Nos. 12, 29/30; 1991: Nos. 1-27 (Folder 11)
    - 1991: Nos. 28-41, 43, 44, 46/47 (Folder 12)
  - Lietuva Etnines Kulturas Biciuliams, 1989: 1 issue (unnumbered) (Folder 13)
  - Lietuvos Darbininkas (Kaunas), 1990: No. 9 (Folder 14)
  - Lietuvos Evangeliku Kelias (Kaunas), 1990: No. 1 (Folder 15)
  - Lietuvos Jeruzale (Vilnius)
    - 1989: No. 1; 1990: Nos. 2, 3, 6; 1991: Nos. 2-4 (Folder 16)
    - 1992: Nos. 10, 11 (Folder 17)
  - Lietuvos Laisves Lyga (Vilnius), 1989: No. 10 (Folder 18)
  - Lietuvos Paminklai (Vilnius), 1990: No. 1 (Folder 19)
  - Lietuvos Socialdemokratas (Vilnius), 1989: No. 1 (Folder 20)
  - Lietuvos Ukininko Patarejas (Kaunas), 1990: No. 3; 1991: No. 8 (Folder 21)
  - Lithuania/Lietuva (Vilnius), 1991: No. 1 (Folder 22)
  - The Lithuanian Review (Vilnius), 1990: Nos. 2-9; 1991: No. 1 (Folder 23)
  - Lithuanian Weekly (Vilnius), 1992: No. 36 (Folder 24)
  - Litovskii Ierusalim (Vilnius), 1992: No. 11 (Folder 25)
  - Lygus Ir Drauge (Vilnius), 1989: No. 7; 1990: No. 5 (Folder 26)
  - Merkurijus (Vilnius), 1990: Nos. 2, 6; 1991: Nos. 1-5 (Box 6., Folder 1)
  - Mokslo Lietuva (Vilnius), 1990: Nos. 3-8; 1991: Nos. 3-5, 8 (Folder 2)
  - Musu Birza (Vilnius), 1990: Nos. 1, 2, 5, 6, 8 (Folder 3)
  - Musu Praetis (Vilnius), 1990: No. 1 (Folder 4)
  - Musu Rupesciai (Vilnius), 1990: No. 20; 1991: No. 8 (Folder 5)
  - Musu Rupintojelis, 1989: No. 8 (Folder 6)
  - Musu Zinios (Taurageje), 1989: Nos. 4, 5, 14; 1990: No. 3, 4 (Folder 7)
  - Muzikos Barai (Vilnius), 1989: No. 1; 1990: No. 7; 1991: Nos. 1, 3-15 (Folder 8)
  - Nepriklausoma Lietuva (Vilnius), 1990: No. 1; 1992: Nos. 43-45, 49 (Folder 9)
  - Neringa (Nida), 1989: No. 10 (Folder 10)
  - Opozicija (Vilnius)
    - 1991: No. 3; 1992: Nos. 9, 17-21, 23-26, 28-31 (Folder 11)
    - 1992: Nos. 34-37 (Folder 12)
  - Padek Sau (Vilnius), 1992: Nos. 10, 11, 14, 15 (Folder 13)
  - Pasaulis (Kaunas), 1989: No. 6 (Folder 14)
  - Pasaulis (Vilnius), 1990: No. 23; 1991: Nos. 1, 3, 9, 10, 13/14; 1992: Nos. 9/12 (Folder 15)
  - Pavasario Ziedas (Moletai), 1989: No. 2 (Folder 16)
  - Permainos (Vilnius)
    - 1990: Nos. 2-6, 9-22, 24-36 (Folder 17)
    - 1991
      - Nos. 1-20 (Box 7., Folder 1)
      - Nos. 21-30, 32-34 (Folder 2)
  - Perspektyvos (Druskininkai), 1990: No. 2 (Folder 3)
  - Pirmadienis (Vilnius), 1992: Nos. 103-105 (Folder 4)
  - Politika (Vilnius), 1991: No. 22; 1992: No. 16 (Folder 5)
  - PoTO (Vilnius), 1990: Rugsejis (Folder 6)
  - Pozicija (Vilnius), 1990: Nos. 5, 7-13; 1991: No. 1 (Folder 7)
  - Prisikelimas (Kaunas), 1990: No. 4 (Folder 8)
  - Privatizavimo Biuletenis (Vilnius), 1991: No. 1 (Folder 9)
  - Proskyna (Vilnius)
    - 1989: Nos. 1-3; 1990: Nos. 1, 3, 4 (Folder 10)
    - 1991: Nos. 1-5, 7 (Folder 11)
  - Provincija (Alytus), 1990: Nos. 1-3. 6-10, 20 (Folder 12)
  - Ramura (Vilnius), 1989: Nos. 1, 13 (Folder 13)
  - Reklama (Vilnius), 1991: No. 24 (Box 8., Folder 1)
  - Respublika (Vilnius), 1991: No. 24 (Folder 2)
  - Sajudis (Kaisiadorys), 1990: No. 1 (Folder 3)
  - Sajudzio Zinios (Vilnius)
    - 1988: Nos. 1-40, 42-45, 47, 48, 50-60 (Folder 4)
    - 1989: Nos. 61-74, 81-86 (Folder 5)
  - Salcia (Saleininkai), 1990: Nos. 14, 16, 19, 21, 22; 1991: Nos. 1, 5, 9, 11, 54 (Folder 6)
  - Salonas EC (Vilnius), 1991: No. 1 (Folder 7)
  - Sandrava (Panevezys), 1990: No. 1 (Folder 8)
  - Santara (Kaunas), 1989: No. 3 (Folder 9)
  - Saskaityba (Vilnius), 1990: No. 3; 1991: No. 5 (Folder 10)
  - Sausis (Kaunas), 1991: No. 2 (Folder 11)
  - Savaites Krivule (Siauliai), 1989: Nos. 1-11; 1990: Nos. 1-16, 37 (Folder 12)
  - Savaites Skelbimai (Kaunas), 1990: No. 6 (Folder 13)
  - Savaites Zinios (Vilnius), 1989: No. 3 (Folder 14)
  - Savaites Zodis (Vilnius), 1992: No. 12 (Folder 15)
  - Savanoris (Vilnius), 1991: Nos. 2, 5, 8 (Folder 16)
  - Savinkas (Vilnius), 1992: No. 1 (Folder 17)
  - Seimininke (Kaunas), 1991: No. 7 (Folder 18)
  - Skambek Daina (Vilnius), 1990: Nos. 1/2 (Folder 19)
  - Skuodo Zodis (Skuodas), 1989: Nos. 4, 5, 7-9; 1990: Nos. 5, 6 (Folder 20)
  - S.O.S. (Vilnius), 1991: No. 28 (Folder 21)
  - Studentu Dienos (Kaunas), 1990: Nos. 1/2 (Folder 22)
  - Szalcza (Szalczininkaj), 1990: Nos. 3-5; 1991: Nos. 21-23 (Folder 23)
  - Talka (Vilnius), 1988: Nos. 7/8 (Folder 24)
  - Taurosta (Jonava), 1990: No. 11 (Folder 25)
  - Tautos Kultura (Vilnius), 1990: No. 1 (Folder 26)
  - Teviskes GAMTA (Vilnius), 1990: No. 1 (Folder 27)
  - Teviskes Zinios (Kaunas), 1991: Nos. 21, 49, 133 (Folder 28)
  - Tevynes Sargas (Vilnius), 1992: Nos. 1/2 (Folder 29)
  - Tiesa (Vilnius)
    - 1991: No. 9 (Folder 30)
    - 1992
      - Nos. 33, 35, 38, 39, 41-46, 48-60 (Folder 31)
      - Nos. 61-73, 75, 76 (Box 9., Folder 1)
  - Tikejimo Zodis (Vilnius), 1988: Nos. 1, 3, 4 (Folder 2)
  - Traku Zeme (Trakai), 1990: No. 1 (Folder 3)
  - Tremtinys (Kaunas), 1992: No. 21 (Folder 4)
  - Tribuna (Vilnius), 1989: Nos. 1, 3, 5, 10 (Folder 5)
  - Trimitas (Kaunas), 1990: Nos. 2, 5; 1991: Nos. 3, 4, 9, 11, 14; 1992: Nos. 10, 12 (Folder 6)
  - Tukas (Kaunas), 1991: No. 1 (Folder 7)
  - Turizmo Horizontai (Vilnius), 1990: No. 10 (Folder 8)
  - Ugniagesys (Vilnius), 1990: Nos. 1-4, 6, 9, 10 (Folder 9)
  - Ukinink Palarejas (Kaunas), 1990: Nos. 2, 5-9, 17 (Folder 10)
  - Universitas Vilnensis (Vilnius), 1991: No. 6 (Folder 11)
  - Universiteto Zurnalistas (Vilnius), 1988: Nos. 13, 14 (Folder 12)
  - Upas (Kaunas), 1990: Nos. 2, 9, 13 (Folder 13)
  - Uputis (Kaunas), 1991: No. 1 (Folder 14)
  - Vadyba (Vilnius), 1989: No. 1 (Folder 15)
  - Vakarines Naujienos (Vilnius), 1990: Nos. 71, 214 (Folder 16)
  - Valstybes Zinios (Vilnius), 1990: Nos. 20-22 (Folder 17)
  - Valstieciu Laikrastis (Vilnius), 1991: No. 54 (Folder 18)
  - Varpas (Vilnius), 1989: No. 10/11 (Folder 19)
  - Varpile (Varena), 1990: No. 11 (Folder 20)
  - Vasario 16 (Kaunas), 1989: Nos. 1-3, 5, 8, 10, 13; 1990: Nos. 1, 2, 4-17; 1992: No. 21 (Folder 21)
  - Vasaris (Kaunas), 1991: Nos. 2, 3 (Folder 22)
  - Verslininkas (Ukmerge), 1990: No. 1 (Folder 23)
  - Viftis (Vilnius), 1991: No. 5 (Folder 24)
  - Vilniaus Balsas (Vilnius), 1989: Nos. 1, 2, 5, 9, 12-14; 1990: Nos. 2, 4-6, 9-11, 13-22, 25, 26 (Folder 25)
  - Vilniaus Laikrastis (Vilnius)
    - 1990: Nos. 2-6, 8, 9, 11-13 (Box 10., Folder 1)
    - 1991: Nos. 2, 6, 16, 18-21, 24 (Folder 2)
  - Viltis (Vilnius), 1988: No. 4; 1992: Nos. 30-32 (Folder 3)
  - Vokieciu Zinios Lietuvoje (Klaipeda), 1989: No. 1; 1990: Nos. 1, 2 (Folder 4)
  - Voruta (Trakai), 1990: Nos. 3, 6; 1991: Nos. 2-8, 10-12, 21, 22 (Folder 5)
  - Vytis (Chicago), 1980: Nos. 5, 6 (Folder 6)
  - Vytis (Vilnius), 1990: No. 1 (Folder 7)
  - Zalioji Lietuva (Vilnius)
    - 1989: Nos. 3, 4, 7, 8, 10-12, 13-17, 19-21, 23, 24 (Folder 8)
    - 1990: Nos. 1-13; 1992: No. 54 (Folder 9)
  - Zaltvyksle (Vilnius), 1990: Nos. 1, 2 (Folder 10)
  - Zemaiciu Bendrove (Kretinga), 1991: No. 3 (Folder 11)
  - Zemaiciu Krastas (Mazeikiai), 1989: Nos. 1-6, 8-11 (Folder 12)
  - Zemaiciu Tiesa, 1988: No. 4 (Folder 13)
  - Ziburys (Anyksciai), 1989: No. 10 (Folder 14)
  - Ziemelos, 1991: No. 6 (Folder 15)
  - Ziemgala (Joniskis), 1989: No. 1 (Folder 16)
  - Ziemgala (Pakruojis), 1991: No. 1 (Folder 17)
  - Zingsniai (Radviliskis), 1990: Nos. 1, 7 (Folder 18)
  - Zurnalistu Zinios (Vilnius), 1991: Nos. 3-7 (Folder 19)
  - Zvaigzdikas (Vilnius), 1991: No. 2 (Folder 20)
  - Zvilasnis (Radviliskis), 1989: No. 3; 1990: No. 3 (Folder 21)
  - Zygeivis (Vilnius), 1989: Nos. 2, 4, 5, 9; 1990: Nos. 10, 11 (Folder 22)
- Incremental materials (Box 11-13)
  This addition to the collection has not yet been described. Please let the Hoover Institution Archives know if you would like to see this material described.